Yunari Expedition! Yuna Explorers!
I am Yuna Waki! I am Yoka Yoshimura!
Please come with me!
I am Yunari Expedition!
Today, we have Yuna and Waka.
I'm Yuna Waka.
It's been a while.
Since we ate crepes, what?
You ate a crepe?
Have you had hot crepes since then?
It was about 3 years ago.
That's the crepe I had.
I have a question for you two.
Do you guys know Rakugo?
Yes, we do.
Have you ever seen or heard of it?
Not on TV?
Yes, yes, yes.
By the way, I'm doing it before Koharuko.
They fight over the zabuton.
They say funny things and fight over the zabuton.
I see.
Do you want to go that deep?
Like, like, carrying around a zabuton.
There?
Don't underestimate it!
That's a lot of work, too.
Today we have a little something for you.
Today's exploration is
Let's learn how to perform Rakugo!
Wow!
What's up with that?
The exploration team is a little something.
We thought it would be a good idea for the two of us to learn about traditional Japanese arts and calligraphy,
So today we have invited a teacher to join us. Today's teacher is Yoichi Shunputei. Please join us.
I look forward to working with you.
First of all, may I ask you all to introduce yourselves in front of the camera?
My name is Yoichi Harufutei, and I am from Sendai City, Miyagi Prefecture. I am from Sendai City, Miyagi Prefecture.
I look forward to working with you.
I don't need a "Yu" or anything like that. I don't think that traditional performing arts are quite right. I don't want to be a "Yu" or anything.
Today, two of us would like to experience a traditional art form, so we would like you to teach us how to perform Rakugo.
We would like you to teach us how to perform Rakugo.
You are right, Yoichi-sensei, aren't you?
You look young, don't you?
I am the youngest member of the school association I belong to.
I'm the youngest.
I'm 26 years old.
You can't see it... but...
He's terrible.
The director.
It's too much.
He's wearing a kimono, too.
He's the youngest.
That's right.
Amazing.
You're younger than that, aren't you?
I'm four years younger.
Four different?
All four.
The same age?
Is that so?
That's good.
I saw that some of the other members were born in 2005.
Some of them are only 19 years old.
I see.
That's good.
I look forward to working with you.
What do you mean when you say you two will teach us today?
Let's try some of the more famous ones.
Like the sobas?
I've seen it before.
You can ask questions about that and other things today. Let's learn from them.
Do you really think so? I was wondering what club you were in.
There? That's how you got into rakugo, isn't it?
That's true. I wonder what kind of route he took.
Today, we're going to take a look at Yoichi Sensei in the nude. He may have taken off his kimono at the end. Like a baseball trainee.
You've been on board with us quite a bit, haven't you? Thank you very much.
Well then, please join us today, Ryoichi Sensei.
First, we're going to have a question-and-answer period. We're going to ask the teacher a lot of questions.
If you two have anything to say...
You are a rakugo storyteller. Why are you interested in rakugo?
How did you first get into it?
My father was a rakugo fan.
Really?
We always had CDs and DVDs of all kinds of greats at home.
It was a weird house.
He took me to Rakugo as a kid, like going to the movies.
It was an art form that was pretty familiar to me.
I've always loved rakugo, so it didn't really feel strange to me.
Oh, your father didn't do rakugo?
No. I like to listen to Rakugo.
I joined the drama club when I was in high school, but there was only one member.
There were only two of us, including me.
I was doing rakugo, and the other one was doing debayashi, the music for the performance.
I don't need that kind of music for club activities, right?
I really didn't play sports at all in that kind of environment, but in junior high school I played soccer, and then I played soccer, and then I played soccer in the gym.
I was the president of the student council at the time, and I did some comic storytelling at the school festival, or something like that.
I was also doing some kind of comedy act.
Did you like comedy?
Yes, I like comedy. All the time.
Did you watch it every week? The laugh point?
No, the laugh point. To be honest, I didn't watch much.
Really? Really?
Not many people like rakugo enough to want to be a storyteller.
Not many people who like rakugo watch that show.
You don't watch it? Surprisingly, yes.
It's a general affairs type show.
Maybe it's old men who listen to rakugo too much,
There are people who don't like Rakugo.
I see.
This is a bit complicated,
Do you understand that "Laugh-In" is not Rakugo?
It's called "rakugo.
Yes, it is.
There is also the Japan Grand Prix.
If you do well in the Japanese Grand Prix, one yellow bar flashes,
If you do well in the Japanese Grand Prix, a yellow bar flashes.
In the Japanese Grand Prix, a yellow bar flashes when you do one good zabuton, but instead of that, the zabuton is a point system,
In rakugo, you sit on a zabuton by yourself and turn to the left and to the right, playing different characters as the story progresses.
Rakugo is a form of storytelling in which you sit on a zabuton by yourself and act out the story by turning to the left and to the right as different characters play out the story.
So you wanted to become an apprentice right after you graduated from high school? When I was a freshman in high school.
I applied to become an apprentice to my master Ichinosuke when I was in my first year of high school.
He told me that since I was a freshman, I had just started high school.
Since you've just started, you should finish high school.
He told me that if I still didn't change my mind, I could come back.
I spent all three years of high school trying to get his hand.
After I graduated, I went back the next day or so to see him again.
I went backstage at a rakugo show that he was going to perform at.
I graduated.
You can go backstage?
Yes, I'd go backstage if I thought I could.
Liver
Idols are more demanding than you think, right?
Yes.
Rakugo performers get in a lot.
Oh, my God!
You can go to the cliff?
They can go all the way to the pond.
What's that?
You know, like, a lesson.
You know? The rite of passage.
You wrap some money and stuff like that.
I want to give this to a comedian.
I'd like to give this to a comedian...
and the staff will let me through.
Wow!
This time, the security is very tight.
LOL.
I guess.
I know.
So I went there.
I said I'd like to give you a letter.
Wow.
That's how it was.
What kind of training do you get when you become an apprentice?
Rakugo.
You know, like that.
Like living in a house.
Like doing the laundry and cooking.
I know it's not very exciting, but...
But we didn't have that kind of training.
If you don't have time for that, learn to talk.
I see.
That's how we were taught.
We weren't strict at all.
Of course, I had to do a lot of bag-carrying.
But that's about it.
It's like sitting in the front seat.
You sit in the front seat for about four years after you join the school.
During that time, I had a lot of different masters.
I put on kimonos for other masters besides my own master.
or folding kimonos for other masters, or serving tea, etc.
Each master has his or her own way of folding kimonos.
There are different ways to fold kimonos depending on the master.
The way they like their tea is also different.
There are about 1,000 people in the east and west dressing rooms.
You have to learn them all.
This master likes hot, strong tea.
This master likes cold tea.
There's a master who doesn't like green tea, he likes oolong tea.
I don't know.
I had to learn all the different jumbled things.
That was for four years.
It was like an apprenticeship.
Everyone goes through it.
But it's not that bad... but when you say "hard training"...
What is rakugo?
The line between "rakugo" and "rakugo" is becoming blurred with the increase of new rakugo.
If a professional rakugo storyteller wears a kimono, sits on a cushion and speaks
Some people say that's already rakugo.
Classical rakugo is generally stories that were written in the Edo period or the Meiji and Taisho periods.
The basic idea of rakugo is that one person performs different parts of the story.
I see.
You're quite young now, Yochi.
How many young people are in your Rakugo audience?
I don't know.
Yes, there are.
There are no people of my generation anymore.
When it comes to minors, it's really...
Why did you come? They're like, "Why did you come?
It's like they came in by mistake.
Sometimes there are students in school uniforms in the audience.
They're often talked to by the guys around them.
What are you doing here?
I came to school. I know you're working hard.
It's like a good demonstration of your youth, isn't it?
I was like that too.
I heard that he wanted the young people to see more rakugo.
I'm sure he'll grow to love rakugo when he becomes a grandmother, if he's never been exposed to it.
If they don't have any contact with Rakugo, the culture itself will disappear.
If that happens, the culture of rakugo itself will disappear.
I see. So today, I was wondering if you could teach us the basics of how to perform.
Okay, soba noodles.
I've seen this before.
Receiving it...
Yes.
Yes, sir.
Oh!
I see it.
It's hot.
I'm so happy.
So, this is just the rudimentary stuff?
Is this the basics?
I'm used to doing the basics in an easy-to-understand way, but...
But it's not like it's a required subject at all.
It's not like it's a required course or anything, but it's just something that's mentioned a few times.
It's not like you have to be the first person to learn it.
It's not like you have to be the starter and learn this first.
First of all, I decide the size of the bowl in my mind, and I say it's about this size.
Soba.
I see... she doesn't have much taste.
She looks like she has it.
Like you're holding it.
I see... I can imagine the length in my mind as I hold it up.
I see.
So you've already decided.
It's hot, right?
Let it cool down a little bit.
And then suck it all at once.
Why is it so hard?
I feel like, you know...
I feel like an idiot.
What do you mean?
I feel like I ate too much buckwheat noodles and now I feel like an idiot.
Is there anyone like that?
Someone who ate so much soba that he became an idiot.
It's like I was delusional and started eating.
Oh, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
I don't know, I choreographed the dance.
I'm sure there might be soba noodles there.
Like, please try to eat soba
Oh, yeah, yeah, sure, sure.
I like that. I'd like you to do that.
But this "ssururu" sound, is it okay?
It depends on the person.
You put your tongue against your inner cheek, or somewhere above your gums, or your cheek, or somewhere else.
And make it shake with the air.
I have an inner cheek, so it's difficult.
Oh, that's good. That's good.
Oh, but it's going to work. I don't know what I'm doing.
Yes, it's absolutely fine, but...
But I'm going to try it. I'm going to try it.
Please do it.
Oh, man...
Cio!
Ha-ha-ha-ha.
How is it?
The noodles were very soupy.
A lot of broth.
It's hard to tell.
It's difficult, isn't it?
It's difficult. I don't rinse the noodles in the first place.
Foreigner type.
But I hear there are a lot of girls like that these days.
Is that so?
Like they can't rinse their noodles.
I see. So that's it.
I see.
I was just thinking.
You said you were going to put it on here.
It's counting down.
It's been there for a while now.
It came out here... like a person who has buckwheat noodles stuck in here.
You're too focused on putting it on your cheek, it has to make a sound.
If you don't put it on here, it won't make a sound.
Maybe I'm putting too much on my cheeks.
It's got to make a sound.
It doesn't come out, but my face goes funny.
It makes my face look funny, and when I do it like this.
I look like a person who's trying to get rid of his face.
If you work hard, you'll be fine.
I'll try it.
It's hot.
That's a nice little trick you're doing.
It's good.
It's so hot.
Oh!
Udon noodles are so good!
Why does the left side of the buckwheat noodle stand up higher than the right?
It's disgusting!
It's like you're slurping on that side.
It's really stupid when amateurs do it.
That's how difficult it is.
Surprisingly.
Did it take you long to do this?
I did it rather quickly.
That's amazing.
That's because you've seen so many of them. You've got a good image of them.
Yeah, I've been watching them since I was a kid.
It's like a thing.
Things? You do things, don't you? When you were little.
Yes, I did.
Yes, they do. They also slurp udon noodles.
Is that soba noodles?
That was soba.
What?
There are stories where udon noodles are served.
Yes.
Not only udon.
No?
They change the way they slurp it.
Oh, wow.
A little thicker?
You slurp it a little thicker, but not too much.
What's that?
I'm not sure, but I'll give it a try.
Udon noodles.
Yeah, yeah...
And then you eat a lot of udon over here. No.
If you do this all the time, it'll feel like you're really eating.
Hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey
I eat a lot off the table, that's great
4 is a bullet
I'm on a diet now, I'm not a representative of the food
It's a prefecture...
I've heard there's a difference between soba and udon.
I've never tried it, but it's thinner than soba.
He's giving me a difficult task.
He wants me to do that too.
I want to see it.
I'll give it a try.
Bye.
That was fat.
A little thick.
But...
It's a little thick.
That was fast.
Somen noodles.
You're right.
It's thin.
It's a little thin.
It's done.
That's great!
What happens when you do it in the sink?
Flowing Somen.
Oh, my God!
They're selling it like crazy today.
It's flowing!
Floating somen
Oh, I got it, I got it
Oh!
It's cool
I don't know what's right
Floating Somen is fun!
Is there anything else?
Manako and her gestures?
I just used my sense.
There's also a hand towel.
Just these two props.
This alone expresses various things.
Just the hand towels.
Shall we do this one?
What are we doing now?
Guess.
Oh, yes!
Banana.
That's good, that's good.
Baked sweet potato.
Banana.
The correct answer is.
It was a baked banana.
No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
Oh, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
That was close.
No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
But you know what?
I did it as if it was a baked potato.
I see.
So you think it's good to end a story?
Give an ending to the story.
That's right.
That's why it says to tell an ending.
I usually give an ending to my stories.
For example, there is an old tale about Momotaro.
Momotaro is a bit different when it is a rakugo story,
Once upon a time, there was an old man and an old woman.
Once upon a time, there was an old man and an old woman. The old man went to the mountains to mow the lawn, and the woman went to the river to do her laundry.
When the grandmother was washing her clothes in the river, a big sweet potato came out of the river,
While she was washing clothes in the river, a big sweet potato came dribbling down from the river,
The old lady made a baked sweet potato and ate it all by herself.
She was so hungry.
One big one.
Bwaaaaah!
The smell wafted toward the old man at the top of the mountain.
It was wafting toward the old man at the top of the mountain,
Grandpa mowed the grass, not the lawn.
Wow!
Did you get it?
Did you get it? I'm just a little slow to react now, is everything all right?
That's great!
This is how we ride each other and make tea.
And then we'll make it easy for them.
He said he mowed the grass, he mowed the grass.
I cut the grass.
It's a little difficult to explain.
Yes, it is.
That's great.
I see.
It's like a short, short rakugo.
I'm sure you've seen a lot of short stories.
I'm sure you've seen a lot of short stories, but today I'd like to present a short story
I think we're going to have a place
I think we're going to set up a place for you two to tell us a story.
At e-BEANS...
There's a stage on the 4th floor.
You're right.
We can use it as much as we want.
Yes, sir.
So today, I've prepared a short story for you, and we're going to perform it one by one.
Then let's move to the 4th floor and have them perform.
Okay, let's move to the 4th floor now.
Okay, Yuna, you'll start the demonstration on the stage.
Yes, I'll do my best.
Please tell us your enthusiasm.
Well, Minari and the stage has been prepared for us.
I'm going to make you laugh out loud with my first song.
Please do your best.
I'll do my best!
Suddenly...
I'm Hazuki. I'd like to take a seat.
This is a tavern, isn't it?
Hey, you come here often, are you from the neighborhood?
Well, I'm, after I leave this restaurant, I turn the first corner, and the second house is...
No, no, no, no, Mr. An, that's my house.
What?
That's my house.
No, it's mine, too.
No, I... no, I...
We had a fight.
Oh, no.
A customer saw that.
General, general.
I got in a fight over there.
Are you all right? Stop him.
I'm fine.
They're father and son.
How's it going?
Thank you very much.
And now, let's go to Mr. Waka.
I'm looking forward to it.
I'm sure he'll bring a breath of fresh air to the world of rakugo.
Excellent.
Do your best.
I'll do my best.
Let's go.
Thank you very much.
Yes, I'm Gallmari.
I'm Tegalmari. Nice to meet you.
Thank you very much.
Let me tell you a story.
A couple went for a drive.
They had an accident and died.
But their chimpanzee was the only one who survived.
The police questioned the chimpanzee.
Chimpanzee, you...
You can speak human language.
So what was your father doing
What was your father doing when the accident happened?
I see.
That could have been the cause of the accident.
Then what was your mother doing
What was your mother doing?
What was she doing?
Well, that could have been the cause of the accident.
Then what were you doing when you had your accident?
Ookay! Ookie! Ookie!
Wookiee!
Thank you very much.
And that concludes our two demonstrations.
How was it, sir?
It was great!
You've only been teaching for about 5 minutes.
Until you learn it.
It's amazing.
You learned faster than I did in the beginning.
That's for sure.
I guess all the dancing and singing
I'm sure it really comes to life.
Maybe he has stage guts.
That was amazing.
I'm glad.
How did you two do?
Iwata.
It's difficult, but I think I could use it if I learned something.
If I'm asked to do a trick...
I'd tell them a story.
A good laugh.
I could do it as entertainment at a gathering or something.
I'd like to do it somewhere.
How was it, Mr. Wakasa?
Yes, it was very difficult to tell a story.
It was really difficult, but it was a great test of my acting ability, and a lot of fun.
Thank you very much. I usually do easy, and depending on the time, my performance is good or not so good,
I sometimes feel depressed, like, "Oh, I didn't do well today,
But seeing the two of you today, I felt something was wrong.
But seeing the two of you today, I felt something different, something like the importance of just going through with it with a smile.
I felt like I was being taught a lesson.
I'm an idol now!
It was amazing.
Everyone watching you had a smile on their face.
It really is an amazing talent.
I'm glad to hear that you were praised so highly by your teacher.
I'm so glad.
Maybe I'll become your apprentice.
You're light on your feet, aren't you?
You'll be doing some events at Ebean's in the future?
That's right.
I'm thinking of doing something for beginners.
I'm planning an event where I'm going to explain to them in an easy-to-understand way how to enjoy themselves.
We're planning an event where we'll explain the fun without force, and give an easy-to-understand talk about how to have fun.
We'd love to see you there.
It's going to be fun!
Come check it out, and maybe you'll see my two disciples.
Sure.
Not at all.
Thank you.
I'd love to have you come.
So today...
It's our first time to try Rakugo.
Yoichi-san taught us everything from 1 to 100.
Thank you very much.
It was a valuable experience.
We are from Sendai, aren't we? Yes, we are from Tohoku, too, so I hope we can do something together somewhere.
I hope you all enjoy Rakugo. That was today's Ikinari Tankentai.
Bye bye!